There's one more thing you can do to protect yourself from experiencing the symptoms of Alzheimer's, even if you have the full-blown disease pathology ablaze in your brain. It has to do with neural plasticity and cognitive reserve. Remember, the experience of having Alzheimer's is ultimately a result of losing synapses. The average brain has over a hundred trillion synapses, which is fantastic; we've got a lot to work with. And this isn't a static number. We gain and lose synapses all the time, through a process called neural plasticity. Every time we learn something new, we are creating and strengthening new neural connections, new synapses. In the Nun Study, 678 nuns, all over the age of 75 when the study began, were followed for more than two decades. They were regularly given physical checkups and cognitive tests, and when they died, their brains were all donated for autopsy. In some of these brains, scientists discovered something surprising. Despite the presence of plaques and tangles and brain shrinkage -- what appeared to be unquestionable Alzheimer's -- the nuns who had belonged to these brains showed no signs of having the disease while they were alive. How can this be? We think it's because these nuns had a high level of cognitive reserve, which is a way of saying that they had more functional synapses. People who have more years of formal education, who have a high degree of literacy, who engage regularly in mentally stimulating activities, all have more cognitive reserve. They have an abundance and a redundancy in neural connections. So even if they have a disease like Alzheimer's compromising some of their synapses, they've got many extra backup connections, and this buffers them from noticing that anything is amiss. Let's imagine a simplified example. Let's say you only know one thing about a subject. Let's say it's about me. You know that Lisa Genova wrote "Still Alice," and that's the only thing you know about me. You have that single neural connection, that one synapse. Now imagine you have Alzheimer's. You have plaques and tangles and inflammation and microglia devouring that synapse. Now when someone asks you, "Hey, who wrote 'Still Alice?'" you can't remember, because that synapse is either failing or gone. You've forgotten me forever. But what if you had learned more about me? Let's say you learned four things about me. Now imagine you have Alzheimer's, and three of those synapses are damaged or destroyed. You still have a way to detour the wreckage. You can still remember my name. So we can be resilient to the presence of Alzheimer's pathology through the recruitment of yet-undamaged pathways. And we create these pathways, this cognitive reserve, by learning new things. Ideally, we want these new things to be as rich in meaning as possible, recruiting sight and sound and associations and emotion. So this really doesn't mean doing crossword puzzles. You don't want to simply retrieve information you've already learned, because this is like traveling down old, familiar streets, cruising neighborhoods you already know. You want to pave new neural roads. Building an Alzheimer's-resistant brain means learning to speak Italian, meeting new friends, reading a book, or listening to a great TED Talk. And if, despite all of this, you are someday diagnosed with Alzheimer's, there are three lessons I've learned from my grandmother and the dozens of people I've come to know living with this disease. Diagnosis doesn't mean you're dying tomorrow. Keep living. You won't lose your emotional memory. You'll still be able to understand love and joy. You might not remember what I said five minutes ago, but you'll remember how I made you feel. And you are more than what you can remember. Thank you. (Applause)
Vous pouvez faire une autre chose pour vous empêcher de vivre les symptômes d'Alzheimer, même si la pathologie est bien déclenchée dans votre cerveau. Cela est lié à la plasticité neuronale et la réserve cognitive. Souvenez-vous, avoir Alzheimer est finalement le résultat de la perte de synapses. Le cerveau moyen a plus de cent billions de synapses, ce qui est fantastique ; nous avons beaucoup de matière. Ce nombre n'est pas statique. Nous gagnons et perdons constamment des synapses via un processus appelé plasticité neuronale. Quand nous apprenons quelque chose de nouveau, nous créons et renforçons de nouvelles connexions neuronales, de nouvelles synapses. Durant une étude sur 678 nonnes ayant toutes plus de 75 ans au début de l'étude, suivies durant plus de deux décennies, on leur a régulièrement fait passer des examens médicaux, des tests cognitifs et à leur mort, leur cerveau fut autopsié. Dans certains de ces cerveaux, les scientifiques ont fait une découverte surprenante. Malgré la présence de plaques, de nœuds et de rétrécissement du cerveau -- ce qui semblait incontestablement être Alzheimer -- les nonnes qui possédaient ces cerveaux n'avaient montré aucun signe de la maladie durant leur vie. Comment est-ce possible ? Nous pensons que ces nonnes avaient beaucoup de réserve cognitive, elles avaient plus de synapses fonctionnelles. Les gens qui ont plus d'années d'éducation formelle, un degré d'instruction plus élevé, qui participent régulièrement à des activités mentalement stimulantes ont plus de réserve cognitive. Ils ont une abondance et une redondance dans leurs connexions neuronales. Même s'ils ont une maladie comme Alzheimer qui compromet certaines synapses, ils ont beaucoup de connexions de secours et cela leur permet de ne pas remarquer que quelque chose ne va pas. Imaginons un exemple simplifié. Disons que vous ne savez qu'une chose sur un sujet. Disons que c'est à mon propos. Vous savez que Lisa Genova a écrit « Still Alice » et c'est tout ce que vous savez à mon sujet. Vous avez cette connexion neuronale unique, cette unique synapse. Imaginez que vous ayez Alzheimer. Vous avez des plaques, des nœuds, une inflammation et des microglies qui dévorent cette synapse. Quand quelqu'un vous demande qui a écrit « Still Alice », vous ne vous souvenez pas car cette synapse dysfonctionne ou n'existe plus. Vous m'avez oubliée. Et si vous en aviez appris un peu plus à mon sujet ? Disons que vous ayez appris quatre choses. Imaginons que vous ayez Alzheimer et trois de ces synapses sont endommagées ou détruites. Vous avez encore moyen de contourner les décombres. Vous vous souvenez de mon nom. Nous pouvons résister à la présence de la pathologie d'Alzheimer en utilisant des chemins qui ne sont pas encore endommagés. Nous créons ces chemins, cette réserve cognitive, en apprenant de nouvelles choses. Idéalement, nous voulons que ces choses soient aussi riches de sens que possible, utilisant la vue, le son, les associations et les émotions. Cela ne veut pas dire faire des mots croisés. Vous ne voulez pas seulement retrouver une information déjà apprise car c'est comme emprunter des rues familières, connues, naviguer dans des quartiers que vous connaissez déjà. Vous voulez paver de nouvelles routes neuronales. Développer un cerveau résistant à Alzheimer, c'est apprendre à parler italien, rencontrer de nouveaux amis, lire un livre ou écouter une super présentation TED. Et si, malgré tout cela, un jour on vous diagnostique atteint d'Alzheimer, voici trois leçons que j'ai apprises de ma grand-mère et des dizaines de personnes que je connais et qui ont cette maladie. Le diagnostic ne signifie pas que vous mourrez demain, continuez à vivre. Vous ne perdrez pas votre mémoire émotionnelle, vous comprendrez toujours l'amour et la joie. Vous ne vous souviendrez pas de ce que j'ai dit il y a 5 minutes mais vous vous souviendrez de ce que vous avez ressenti. Vous êtes plus que ce dont vous vous souvenez. Merci. (Applaudissements)